[Music]
Stanford
University we were we were waste deep
into dur into the dur land the dur sea
well we didn't get to the daxi
yet uh but before we continue with the
three dimens before I'll do a little
review of the dra equation that we
studied and then we'll go into the
three-dimensional version three space
onetime Dimension as a real world dur
equation but before we do let's uh go
back and review what not review
generalize what we said about second
quantization the field Theory the fields
governing multiple multiple particle
systems we made them out of creation and
Annihilation
operators what's the difference between
firm Neons and bons in that
respect and the difference is
simple not so
intuitive but
uh rather
straightforward if you have two
bons you can put them into the same
state number
one and um no no problem putting him
into the same
state and what's more the creation and
Annihilation operators all commute with
each
other um nothing uh particular odd
nothing particularly odd about things
which commute with each
other there is something very odd about
things which anti- commute with each
other so let's talk about
anti-commutation
um supposing we have two particles
and we want to say that when we
interchange them that the wave function
or the state Vector should change sign
so let's think about what that would
mean for these operators that we're
constructing
um a particle at X and another particle
at y particle one at one now stands for
Which
slot this is slot one this is slot two
this stands for particle one this stands
for particle 2 x stands for the position
of particle one y stands for the
position of particle 2 neither X nor y
refers to the X and Y coordinates X and
Y are each if you like three-dimensional
positions or one-dimensional positions
depending on the
context that's a state with two
particles one at X and one at y for
bans this is exactly the same thing
as putting particle one at position Y
and particle 2 at position X they're
equal to each
other okay so in particular that would
tell
you how do you make a particle X and
particle y you take
P of
X time P of y a creation or this should
be creation
operators a creation operator for a
particle at x a particle at Y and you
hammer on the
vacuum you let them act on the vacuum
and that creates particle at X and
Y supposing I want to Interchange
particle X or the two particles that's
just interchanging X and
Y that would be side dagger at
y side dagger at
X also vacuum
good now why is this true it's true
because the size commute with each other
you can interchange them this and this
are related very simply by interchanging
the two operators here and if they
commute that just says that side Dagger
of X time side Dagger of Y is the same
as side dag of y * side of X and so it's
guaranteed that with with the objects
and the theory that we've been making up
till now that they satisfy this kind of
Bose statistics this kind of Bon rules
now for
Fons the rule is exactly the same but
with a minus
sign remember that the state Vector of a
system the real physical observable
State Vector of a
system doesn't care about the sign here
but in keeping track of the formulas
it's important to know
that for Fons if you interchange the two
particles you get a minus
sign that must
mean that for Fons if SI here is
representing
Fons that this is the top equation here
the top form formula is minus the bottom
formula and the
mathematics goes with this is just a
statement that for fermans the fields
anti- commute so let's write out what
that means it means side diag of X time
side diag of
y equals minus this over here but let's
shift it to the left hand side and write
that plus side
diager of Y side diager of
x equals
z this object if you take take two
operators and you take their product and
instead of subtracting in the opposite
order you add in the opposite order
that's called the anticommutator
and it's
written instead of a square bracket
instead of a square um commutator
usually written with a curly
bracket P Dagger of X PID Dagger of
y equals
zero
okay in general when you go from Fons to
bosons you just take every commutation
relation and replace it by an
anti-commutation relation and that's how
you go from Fons to bosons now that has
let's see is there anything else yeah
first of all it's quite clear that you
can't have two particles in the same
state for example supposing you wanted
to put two particles at the same
point you want to put two particles at
the same point that corresponds
to multiple let's get rid of this over
here that corresponds to acting with
creation operators at the same point but
this equation over here or let's say
this one over
here that tells us that side diag of x
side diager of
X Time s of
x side diag of X plus side diager of x *
side diager of X that's the
anticommutator of side dagger x with
itself I've just replaced y by X and the
statement here is that that should be
equal to
zero well this operator and this
operator exact the same this is just
twice side diag of x * side diag of x
equal 0 and if something is equal
to if twice something is equal to zero
the thing itself is equal to
zero so trying to put two particles into
the same state always gives you zero
anti-commutation which cannot go in the
same
state there's an interesting peculiarity
here for
bans for bans there's a clear
mathematical distinction between
creation operators and Annihilation
operators
um even if you didn't know what what the
devil these things stood for when you
write out the commutation let's we don't
we don't we have no idea what these
things stand for we just know that
there's this algebraic structure that's
some kind of creation or some sort of
object let's let's not put daggers on
for now it doesn't matter daggers or no
daggers some sort of
objects
commute these things commute no I'm
sorry I wanted to take side dagger
equals one here we are this way equals
one that's a harmonic oscillator or it
could just be a creation and
Annihilation operator for a
bon
okay could you mistake which one is the
ban operator which one is the creation
operator and which one is the
annihilation operator well if you try to
switch them if you try to replace a by a
dagger an a dagger by
a this is very itely not equal to one in
fact what is it equal
to minus one
right commutator if you switch the two
things the commutator changes this is
minus one and you could always tell even
if I didn't label these as a and a
dagger if I just label them as a and b
and ask you which one is the creation
operator and which one is the
annihilation operator what you do is you
look at the commutators and if the
commutator is plus one then the first
one here is the creation operator and
the second one is the annihilation
operator and there's no way to make a
mistake
um and in fact creation operators and
Annihilation operators are fundamentally
different here's the stack of all
possible
States uh Nal 0 Nal 1 Nal
2 creation operators just mathematically
creation operators do not annihilate any
state they just take you up the ladder
and since the ladder never ends a
creation operator never runs into the
problem that an Annihilation operator
does if it annihilates too many times
Annihilation operators when they get
down to the
bottom uh they give zero another way to
say it is that this
spectrum of in going from zero to
Infinity is not the same if you turn it
upside down
uh you can go up to Infinity but you
can't go down uh past zero okay what
about Fons well now you look at the
firon
operators they also have creation and
Annihilation operators the difference
though is that you have anti-commutation
relations for
Fons you also have creation operators
you can create a firon
plus
one anti-cuts are the same if you
interchange why because this is a a
dagger plus a dagger a it doesn't matter
which order they're in so just from the
mathematical structure from the um from
the
algebra there's no difference between
creation oper they do different it's
true they do different things but just
looking at algebra of them you can't
tell the creation operators from the
annihilation operators and another way
of seeing that is just to look at the
possible
um occupation
numbers of a firon let's say it's a
firon with only one state firon is in
the the ground state of the hydrogen
atom okay what can you have the answer
is you either have no particle
or you have one particle you can't have
any more than one and you can't have any
fewer than
zero what does the creation operator do
it takes you from zero to
one but what does it do when it hits
one nuh no State
there annihilates right zero on the
other hand the annihilation operator
takes you
down if there's a particle there sure
enough you can take you down found but
if there's no particle there in the
story you annihilate the state so
there's a complete
symmetry between being empty and being
filled and replace creation operators by
Annihilation
operators now that doesn't mean they're
physically the same it just means the
algebra and the mathematics uh the the
the symbols you can't tell one from the
other yes question had a question back
when you're saying um if you try to have
two Fons in the same place you have side
diager side diager x equals zero um why
is that a why is that a contradiction or
why is that it's not a contradiction it
just gives zero it doesn't give a
state uh a state a zero state is nothing
so but that uh I'm just curious that's
that's so that's that operator is
squared essentially right side diager is
squared yeah yeah if side if if you have
an operator squared does that mean the
operator is
zero no it means the operator Square to
zero no no here look here's a creation
operator the creation operator squared
there's nothing up here for it to give
so it gives zero if you take the
creation for firon for firon if you take
the creation operator squared it's zero
there's nobody here if you take the
annihilation operator squared at zero on
the other hand for
bans uh there is not this symmetry of uh
of filled and empty it's filled it's the
symmetry of filled and empty two
possible States and only two possible
States and no um for for for a single
state of a firon all right that's going
to play a role we'll get back to it what
it says is that in some sense just pure
mathematical sense you can interchange
for uh creation and Annihilation
operators now you may not want to do
that because they have physical
significance but just as a as as as the
algebraic structure of them you can
interchange
them okay let's come back now to the dra
equation the wonderful dra
equation and let's pursue
it various things we want to
understand we already figured out how to
deal with the fact
that the simplest D equation that we
wrote down doesn't have the possibility
of having a mass let's just go back
through it the simplest thing was just
to write an equation which was D by
DT of s let's put an i there i s equals
minus i d by DX s this was for the case
of one dimension now this s here is some
is the wave is a um is let's say a wave
function for a single
particle uh for the moment we're just
doing single particles one particle this
would be the schinger equation for this
would be the hamiltonian over here this
would be the hamiltonian acting on S is
equal to the momentum acting on
S and we will recognize this as just a
theory in which the energy of a particle
is equal to its momentum
okay energy equal momentum is a
relativistic massless
particle for Mass you want
p^2 sorry e e^2 = p^2 + M2 all right so
this was a failure as a theory of
one-dimensional electrons because
one-dimensional electrons moving on a
wire or something have a
mass okay we figured out what to do with
that we introduce a second species of
electrons which this these were right
moving electrons these were waves which
moved strictly to the right the time
derivative is minus their space
derivative that means they move to the
right so wave packets just propagate off
with constant velocity speed of
light okay what you want to do is you
want to invent another species which
propagates to the left so we could call
This One S one and and we invent another
one H S 2 a completely different
particle equals minus P S 2 a particle
whose energy is minus the momentum and
this just interchanges plus momentum in
that direction right with minus momentum
in that direction and so this particle
clearly propagates to the
left then we combined these two
equations by taking S1 and I 2 and
making a column Vector out of
them Quantum mechanically this means the
particle can either be of one type or
the second type so there's a new degree
of Freedom we discovered the new or we
inventing the new degree of Freedom
which is above and beyond the momentum
of the particle it's its handedness does
it move to the right or does it move to
the left incidentally this particle can
have negative energy or positive energy
because P can be positive or negative
but in either case it goes to the
right this one can have positive energy
or negative energy in either case it
goes to the
left okay then we and
then uh we
invented a matrix The Matrix was
alpha alpha oops that's
gamma lie down Alpha get on your side
and be
Alpha and this says that s 1 is an igen
Vector of alpha with igen value + one
and S 2 is an igen Vector of alpha with
minus one and now we can combine these
two equations and just write that h s
this is supposed to be a simple
s h SI is equal to Alpha * P
SI what does this mean this means that
if Alpha is + one H is p if Alpha is
minus one H is minus P so we have both
of them in the same structure here at
the cost of doubling the number of
components of the field
okay that didn't get us any that didn't
get us a mass but at least got us things
going in both
directions and we did one more trick we
invented a another Matrix that's called
beta and that one looks like this one
one now the fact that these happen to be
poy matrices is somewhat incidental at
this point they're just matricies for
the
moment and instead of writing
H is is equal to Alpha p h is equal to
Alpha P that's that equation down
there plus P or minus P depending on the
sign of alpha we added another term beta
*
m okay now here's some things about
Alpha and beta Alpha squ and beta Square
are
1 and Alpha Beta plus beta Alpha
equals zero you can check that just
check that if you multiply them in one
order you get one thing if you multiply
them in the other order you get the
other thing and they cancel you might
say that Alpha and beta anticommute and
it's true but don't confuse that with
the anti-commutation of the uh of the
fields okay so Alpha and beta anti-
commute they each Square to one
now consider H squared that's the square
of the energy that's the operator that
governs the square of the energy well
that's going to have one term which is
Alpha 2 p^ 2 another term which is beta
m^2 and then yet another term which is
Alpha Beta plus beta Alpha P *
m but we were lucky Alpha Beta * beta
Alpha is identically equal to zero and
so the only terms that are there
of
p^2 plus m^2 which is exactly what we
want for a uh relativistic particle with
mass okay so we managed by combining a
left moving and a right moving and then
coupling the left moving and the right
moving through this Matrix beta The
Matrix beta does couple them together we
end up with a particle with a
mass it's in this sense that a mass term
uh is a a mass term in the hamiltonian
is something which sort of switches you
from left moving to Right Moving well it
doesn't really do that it just gives the
particle a mass but you can picture it
as causing transitions between left and
right moving to the left and moving to
the right and if you can have
transitions between left and right you
might start to think well maybe it even
makes sense to think of a particle at
rest sort of a rest
at rest good you can have a massive
particle at rest you can't have a
massless particle what are you doing I'm
filming it oh okay but question um is
there more to the physical
interpretation of having both types of
particles it is what it is I uh is there
more to it we'll get there yeah there
there is more to it but at this point
that's what the that's all there is
you sometimes things are just abstract
uh sometimes that's all there is to
it all right so then comes the question
how do we do this in three dimensions
three dimensions instead of one
dimension three dimensions of
space okay so let's go
back let's
start with what will will turn out to be
the case which is massless will turn out
to be a case which can't have a mass
here's what we're going to do we have
three dimensions of
space
um it wouldn't make sense to have only
one alpha we can have PX we can have py
and we can have pz this looks like it
wants to be some sort of product of a of
a a degree of Freedom with P but p is a
vector what do what what do we get to
make what do we get to multiply by
vectors to make things which are
invariant other vectors we take dot
products of vectors so here's what D
thought to himself he thought this Alpha
here must be a vector if we're going to
multiply it by P and make something
which is rotationally invariant that
means it must have three
components it must have three components
so he said let's try the equation
H
equals alpha. p this means Alpha sub X
PX plus Alpha suby
py plus Alpha subz
pz
okay what do we what do what do the
alphas have to do to make this sensible
for the moment we're not going to try to
make a mass we're going to make a
massless equation so what is the right
formula for a massless particle it's
energy versus momentum
the answer is energy squar equal
momentum squar but that means energy s =
px2 + P Y2 + pz S that's what we want to
get
H2 = px2 + p y^2 + pz
squared what happens if we Square this
thing over here well we'll get terms
which are alpha x^2 * px^ 2 that's okay
that just means we want alpha x s to
equal
1 likewise with alpha
y alpha z^2 =
1 but now we want to make sure the cross
terms aren't there when we multiply out
the cross terms we get PX * py and it
will multiply alpha x alpha y plus alpha
y alpha x that's what will happen so we
better have that alpha x alpha y
plus alpha y alpha x equal
Z and likewise for the
other com combinations same with x and z
same with Y and Z so the ACT says can I
find three
matrices which each one squared is one
and which mutually anti-c commute and
the answer that's easy poly matrices the
three matrices do exactly that okay so
if we say alpha
x is equal to Sigma X the poly Matrix
equals 1 1 0
0 alpha
y
equals Sigma
y equals what Min
-1 sorry minus i i o
o and finally the last one is Alpha
Z equals Sigma Z and that's the easy one
to remember 1 minus
one and we got it in other words our
hamiltonian
H is equal to sigma.
P you can think of
this as a particle
whose well it's a particle that has a
spin that's the sigma and a particle
that and it has a momentum and the
energy is proportional to the dot
product or the component of spin along
the direction of
motion
okay good so it's a massless
particle but it has the odd behavior
that its spin is always um
well let's go back
okay sigma. p
its energy is proportional to the
component of its spin along the momentum
Direction now the component of a spin is
always plus or minus one so it sounds
like there are two cases here one case
where the spin is literally along the
momentum pointing along the momentum and
the other case in which the spin is
opposite to the
momentum in one case the energy is
positive if Sigma is in the same
direction as the momentum sigma. p is
positive if they're oppositely aligned
that's negative so again we have the
situation massless
particle okay a massless particle with
positive and negative energy states and
instead of saying that the particle can
just move along the x- Axis or along the
Y AIS sorry along the x-axis positively
along the x-axis positive this one is
stuck in a different kind of way it's
stuck in that it's momentum or or its um
its energy is sigma. p in other words if
its energy is positive in particular if
it's a positive energy particle then its
spin is always locked to be in the same
direction as the
momentum
so spin drops out of the equation so to
speak it does well that's I that I was
say seems to be we're introducing it
well it certainly doesn't drop out of
the direct
equation where does it come from what do
you mean where does it come from I mean
we just we just uh introdu it because we
know the electon has a
magne that's not why D introduced it dur
introduced it because he wanted to write
a hamiltonian equation I think you mis
reading it falls out it comes in as a
result of oh oh falls out means uh that
it just plopped into your lap no I mean
it the way Mike said which that comes as
a result of comes as a result though
plops into your lap for free right I
thought you meant it falls out that it
doesn't appear in the equation
yeah ah
okay good couple different right um
yeah well
okay look D's logic which is
not necessarily unimpeachable was that
he wanted to write an equation where the
hamiltonian would be written in terms of
the momentum without having some insane
square
root this is the best he could do he
said um I and write H equals alpha. P
because I want it to be linear in the
momentum but then he said what the hell
is Alpha it can't just be a bunch of
numbers and by requiring that h^2 = p^2
he found the direct matrices or these
Alpha M he found this the PO matri es so
he said oh oh I think I've discovered
why this
Spin and in fact he was right in a sense
he was not right that every particle on
Earth has to have a
spin but he was right that the particles
that are described by the Der equation
have a spin and that meant firmians okay
so so far we haven't said what this has
to do with whether they're fion or
bosons uh and we'll come to
that okay but still we have H2 = p^2 and
we don't have a mass H2 = p^2 is the
massless particle what do we have to do
so you might think well what we have to
do is put another beta M here let's try
that what are we going to
require when we Square H we're going to
get the usual Sigma squ p^ s which is
just P
Squared we're going to get assuming that
beta assuming the square of beta is one
again let's assume beta squ is one
again then we'll get an m s term we'll
get h^2 = p^2 +
m^2 plus a cross term and the cross term
will
involve things like let's say PX m i
take the X component of this and I
multiply it by Sigma X beta plus Beta
Sigma
X in other words we want this to be of
course zero we don't want that there so
we want whatever beta is to anti-c
commute with all the poly
matrices that would be great except that
there is no Matrix which
anti-commutation
more
so we give
up or we say why do we have to do why is
it have to be 2 x two
matrices maybe what we have to do is
introduce another binary degree of
Freedom another two value degree of
Freedom so if there's this two value
degree of freedom and another one we
would be talking about 4x4
matrices each particle would have a four
component thing associated with it some
new degree of Freedom you could look for
10 x 10 you could look for 100 by 100
turns out you could look for 3x3 there
on N no 3x3 matrices which have the
anti-commutation relations of the four
necessary matrices here the first case
where you discover that there are four
mutually anti-commuting
matricies is the 4x4 case now the four
the fact that it's 4x4 has nothing to do
with the fact that SpaceTime is
four-dimensional it's just a
mathematical fact about anti-commuting
matrices and I'll show you what they are
you can work them out yourself and see
that they all anti-c
commute oh there incidentally there are
many many different versions or very
very many different representations of
the direct matrices I'll write down what
that means in a minute um you pick one
and you stick with it the all equivalent
they're all absolutely equivalent in the
physics roughly speaking the
relationship between the different
representations nobody would uh nobody
would mind very much if I called the X
Direction the y direction the y
direction the Z Direction the Z
Direction the X Direction so if I called
Sigma y you know if I just permuted them
in some way they'd be just as good
um same is true of the alpha and beta of
the the the uh the direct matrices there
are many many different representations
we just have to pick one and stick with
it all right so what are the rules once
durak realized I don't know what D
realized and what he didn't realize but
once uh in my imagination he realized
that he had to go by 4x4 matrices he
stopped calling these things
Sigma and called them Alpha
same Alpha as up there except they not 2
x two matrices he called them Alpha now
the the fact is I think he wrote this
down before he even thought about the
one-dimensional case and now what we
need is we need four mutually
anti-commuting
matrices Alpha 2 = 1 Alpha X alpha 1
Alpha x^2 = 1 Alpha y^2 = 1 Alpha z^2 =
1 we better also have beta s = 1 but
then we also have to have Alpha X alpha
y plus alpha y alpha
x equal Z that's to make sure that when
we Square this there's no term with PX *
py similar things to this but finally we
have to have for all of the alphas all
three Alphas we have to have I'll just
call it alpha x Time beta plus beta
alpha x also equals z same for y and
same for Z all right and as I
said such matrices exist 4x4 matrices we
call you could call
uh
um you
could but it's not really it's uh
it's it no they don't form a four
Vector uh I'll tell you what forms a
four vector
I'll tell you in a
minute once we get the once we write the
direct equation I'll tell
you okay here are the matrices once you
know them you can forget them because
really all it counts as these properties
here you can work just with the abstract
algebra I think you essentially never
need the actual form of the matrices but
nevertheless you just want to make sure
there are such matrices here's a
particular representation this is not
the one that Dak used this one is called
a po representation of the direct
matrices it's not the
power all right here it is
Alpha the three of them alpha x alpha y
and z z I'll explain this this notation
in a minute these are 4x4
matrices but they consist of blocks 2x
two
blocks in each block there's a 2X two
Matrix in here you put Sigma and I'll
tell you what that means in a minute
here you put minus Sigma and here you
put zero and here you put zero so for
example if I was interested in alpha
x that would be the Matrix Sigma X up
here minus Sigma X down
here 0 0 and what would look like be
again divid it into blocks in this block
put Sigma X which is 1 1 0 0 in this
block down here put 0 -1 - 1 0 all
others
Z same thing for alpha y and Alpha Z so
that gives us the and you can check you
can very quickly check that these
commute with each
other they anti-c commute with each
other as a consequence of the fact that
the sigmas the POI matrices themselves
anti commute with each other and so the
second you start writing down the
products of them you realize you're just
working with the PO matricies in some
very simple way they anti-c commute with
each other and so this kind of thing is
satisfied the only thing we have to
figure out is what beta is and beta is
chosen in the in this representation
to just be 0 1 1 0 but each of these are
2x two blocks so what does this
mean this means in the upper left hand
block here you put Z 0 0 0
0 likewise down
here and what does one over here mean it
means the unit Matrix 1 1 0 0 1 1 0 0
that's beta I am not going to work out
the
anti-cut you know there's nothing to it
other than just multiplying
matrices the anticommutator are zero of
the Alphas with
beta and so we actually have a
hamiltonian whose square is p^2 + m^2
the relativistic uh law of connection
between energy and momentum it sounds
good and it is good
yeah for
the actually it wasn't in that in the
onedimensional case yeah the one right
yeah it's not spin you can't have spin
in One D in one dimension really it was
a spin-like thing but it wasn't really
spin spin requires three dimensions to
spin the you know genuine spin when you
added a m you had to have another degree
of Freedom how is that physically
manifested in some other kind of
thing so what is
it it
is
um it's connected with something called
helicity when we look at the original
equation with Sigma here we found out
that if the particle has positive energy
that means that Sigma has to be aligned
with the momentum here so there was only
one kind of particle with its momentum
momentum and spin along the same axis
what we did in effect here was to put in
another species whose uh energy is the
spin minus the spin times the momentum
so we created another species doubled
everything up and the other species has
what is called the opposite
chirality chirality meaning the
relationship between Spin and momentum
if spin is along the direction of
momentum that's called right-handed like
your right hand your thumb and your
spin opposite is
Left-Handed when we only took the 2x two
matrices we were stuck with particles
with only oneh
handedness okay we put the other one in
we put the other handedness in that gave
us two kinds of particles one which goes
this way one which goes this way and
then we coupled them together by putting
this off
diagonal thing here which mixes the left
mover the the left guys and the right
guys the result was a massive particle
this is the sense in which mass for a
direct particle is a transition or a
coupling between the left-handed
spinning particles and the right-handed
spinning
particles so so massless particles don't
have this char
chirality no they have very good
chirality they don't have they don't
have anything which flips the chirality
yeah the M parles of is
conern
okay did anybody understand what I
said for massless particles the
chirality is conserved it stays
right-handed or it stays left-handed but
the mass term causes transitions between
them it's a term in hamiltonian which
takes one to the other how do I know
that because it's off diagonal it takes
the upper block to the lower block and
mixes
them okay are these
to these um no no the the alpha matrices
are not
the sigma matrices are
querian yeah all right so since you
asked me what about querian I'll just
spend a moment with
him quorans are a way of doing vector
algebra
um they're connected with the sigma
matrices let's go back a step let's take
um complex numbers every complex number
is a plus I B right
A squ and B squ are oh
right every um Herm Mission 2x two
Matrix every Herm Mission 2x two Matrix
Matrix can be written as
a ORD as a thing proportional to the
unit 2x2
matrix plus
I times uh is there an I
um no
I I think I I misspoke I think
uh I think I want to put an eye there
not her Mission forget her Mission
um
Sigma dot some other some
Vector I don't know q a vector
everything can be written as a linear
combination of and these things are
called uh the the 2x two
matrices representing uh things like
this are called quarians but um it's not
going to play any role in what we're
doing is associated with angular
momentum yeah and so is there an energy
term associated with that no nothing
other than this now the now the alpha
here is not actually spin yet we're
going to ask what Alpha means physically
what is uh what is alpha alpha each
Alpha each component here's here's
something true each component of
alpha uh the three of them each
component um oh it's a matrix it has
igen values and the igen values are plus
one and minus one but it has two + one
igen values and 2 minus one igen values
because it's a 4x4
Matrix and the question is what physical
quantity is it representing they don't
commute with each other incidentally so
you can't measure the different
components of alpha simultaneously they
don't commute but you can measure a
component what is the physic physical
meaning of that component and physical
meaning is very
bizarre it's the velocity it's the
velocity of the particle the alphas are
the velocity which means to say that the
expectation value of alpha in any state
is the average is the velocity of the
particle how do you see that
okay what you have to remember is you
have to go
back to the formulas for the time
derivatives of the expectation values of
operators I'll just remind you if I have
some operator let's just call it L A
Herm Mission operator and I'm interested
in its expectation value I won't bother
writing in States here I'll just some
states there some State the expectation
value of L has a value and if the state
changes with time time the expectation
value of L also changes with time do you
remember the formula for
this it's related to the
commutator of the hamiltonian with L now
for the life of me I can never remember
is it plus I or minus
I I don't know and I'm not going to
figure it out it's not hard to figure
out but I'm not going to bother we're
just going to write I we can always
write I doesn't matter we can write plus
I or minus I but then the question is
whether it's commutator of H with l or l
with h and I don't remember but we're
not going to care because uh not
important
okay the time derivative and you take
the expectation value of this the
expectation value the time derivative of
the expectation value of L you can just
think of that as the average time uh
time derivative of L is equal to I time
the commutator of H with L in fact you
can even
erase these uh brackets
here and just write it formally formal
equation that L this okay let's take our
direct
particle and let's consider x dot X is
the x coordinate of the
particle and let's consider using this
formula let's try to figure out what the
velocity operator is what's the operator
which when you measure it it gives you
the
velocity okay so this shouldn't be too
hard it's I times the
commutator of H which is what alpha. P
plus beta
M that's
H commuting with
X well m is just a
number the alphas and betas they commute
with X they're in a different uh they're
in
a a different space they're not in the X
space they're in this 2x2 or 4x4
space so beta and Alpha commute with X
what's the only thing in here which
doesn't commute with
x p which component
p p sub X so when you work out the
commutator this is not
here Alpha commutes with X so that means
you can take it outside and you just
have commutator with p with X which is
what um minus I minus i h
bar okay so this is equal to Min - I * I
is + 1 is equal to alpha alpha subx
so Alpha this crazy it's crazy funny
Theory the
um the velocity of the particle is not
proportional to its
momentum it's given by Alpha so if you
want to know what the velocity of the
particle is you measure
Alpha
now it's
weird can only be plus or minus one in
any direction
right on the other hand Alpha itself is
not
conserved if you oh that's an
interesting question Alpha itself is not
conserved why
not let's see if alpha x is conserved
for that we have to take the
commutator of alpha x of H with alpha
x let's take the commutator of H with
alpha
x that would be the time derivative of
alpha x
X and the problem is that H has in it
alpha y alpha y doesn't commute with
alpha
x it also has Alpha z in it which
doesn't commute with alpha x so the
answer is that the commutator of alpha x
with the hamiltonian is not zero which
means that the particle
accelerates it does a crazy wobbly
motion which is called zidong Zid means
something I don't know it's some German
word meaning um drunk drunken uh drunken
uh drunken Scandinavian it
means
whated
right but of course of course what is
also true is if you look at the uh the
time average of the Velocity the thing
is going this way and this way and this
way but the time average is exactly what
you expect it to be namely the momentum
divided by the
mass uh at least if it's moving slowly
but um Alpha but main point is Alpha is
not the spin it's the velocity it's it's
a vector quantity and spin is a axial
vector quantity it's a pseudo
Vector so I'll tell you what the spin is
it's very easy let's see um where is
Alpha we erased what Alpha is or did
we no
here's
Alpha notice it has this minus Sigma
down there the real spin is just this
it's a different operator it's a
different operator very closely
related uh but it's the spin of it's the
legitimate genuine spin of the
particle so direct discovered a
multiplicity of different states of the
electron one of them had to do with the
chirality which way the spin was or
which way the uh the alpha was oriented
relative to the momentum the other had
to do with the actual spin of the
electron right
so means a free electron in empty space
will vibrate back and forth with no
external forces doesn't that violate uh
something
no no what about uh uh law no no no
Newton's law says the time derivative of
the momentum is
zero it doesn't say the time derivative
of the Velocity is zero it says time
derivative of the momentum is zero in
most situations uh ordinarily momentum
and velocity are related to each other
here the velocity of this particle is
not the
momentum weird isn't
velocity no not for not when there a
mass
right
umel no no I in fact I mean it's true
that in some technical mathematical
sense Alpha is the velocity but it's
also true that it itself is not
conserved and so it's going around like
crazy in some complicated fashion and
there is a Time average of the Velocity
itself you can uh take the time average
of the velocity over a little bit of
time and that is the
momentum that is p over M for slow
electrons for slow electrons you know
it's going around like crazy doing crazy
things but as it doing crazy things it's
moving along um with a smooth
velocity smooth component of the
Velocity which is the momentum and that
you can prove we won't do that now but
uh could there be a measurement which
you measure the instantaneous yeah and
you find it one instant going yeah way
yeah yeah yes the answer is
yes
yeah
right okay now we come to the last thing
for tonight well yeah
probably we come to this strange fact
that the uh that the direct
electron can have both positive energy
and negative energy now for this purpose
we don't even need to think about the
full-blown three-dimensional dur
equation it's enough just to study the
one-dimensional Right Moving
electron just take that case we'll come
back to the three-dimensional case but
all of the interesting uh ideas are
already there just
for the one-dimensional case and even
the one-dimensional case without the
alpha matrices just a pure Right Moving
massless electron that already has Mass
has negative energy if the particle has
positive let's go back what was the
formula for its uh for its energy the
formula for its energy was just H equals
P that's the right I think that's the
right moving electron
yeah not even an alpha that was our
simplest version of the direct equation
if you like it was massless it only went
to the
right but it has both positive and
negative energy iies and the reason it
has negative energies is because P can
be negative there's no restriction here
that P can't be negative okay so we have
to figure out what does this mean
negative energies negative energies are
very dangerous
um
the ground state the vacuum of the world
is not necessarily the state with no
particles in it it's find to be the
state of lowest energy when you take
everything out when when you take all
the energy when you suck out all the
energy from the vacuum or from space
what's left is the vacuum and clearly
the vacuum had better be the lowest
energy otherwise you could lower the
energy past the vacuum and that's a
little bit crazy and uh even worse you
could lower the energy
indefinitely until you have some sort of
monstrous thing with uh with enormously
negative energy what does that mean uh
the V the vacuum is supposed to be empty
space there's not supposed to be
anything that you can remove from it
anymore no way to lower its energy so
what's going on here well D said let's
take the definition of the vacuum to be
the state of lowest
energy what about these negative energy
particles you can put negative energy
particles in if they have negative
energy they lower the energy so you can
lower the energy past zero just by
flooding this thing with many many
negative energy
particles D very cleverly said wait a
minute I know that these particles are
Fons what is the lowest energy State
going to be the lowest energy state is
going to be if I fill it up maximally
with every possible negative energy
particle every negative energy particle
gives you negative energy and if you
fill it up with every negative energy
particle that's as negative as it can
get well wait a minute now why can't you
put they have two negative energy
particles in the same state because
they're
Fons so once you filled up see if they
were bons you'd have trouble no matter
how many of them put in you could always
put in
more so uh if if you had bons which were
negative energy there really would be no
bottom you could just keep putting them
in and putting them in and putting them
in and lower the energy of anything but
D said wait a minute if these are firion
truly Fons you can only put one into a
state if you fill all the possible
negative energy states then your vacuum
is stable because you can't put another
negative energy particle in no room so
to
speak so What dra said was the vacuum if
it's to be the lowest energy state must
be the state in which every negative
energy state is
occupied and then you can't put any more
in this was a this was a intuitive way
to describe some mathematics which I'll
tell you in in a moment what the
mathematics is but it's
correct modern physicists will tell you
they don't like that description because
it uh you know it sounds a little uh the
vacuum is the vacuum it's not full of
stuff but take it let's follow direct
reasoning because it was very effective
said okay let's uh let's fill up all the
negative a energy states and call that
the vacuum then what kind of things can
this system describe okay well we could
come
along here we'll draw a picture to
describe this
thing let's label of course the uh the
momentum is continuous is a continuous
variable but let's just suppose for a
moment that we discretized it
then here's the energies um here are all
the negative energy levels lots of
them
e and what D said is fill these all up
put a particle in every one so it
becomes a um you know sort of
Monolithic thing which you can't put
anymore particles
into and that way you stabilize the
vacuum against more negative energy
particles but what do you have left now
so you said okay you can certainly put a
positive energy particle into this
there's your positive energy
electron but you can do something else
you can
remove a negative energy electron from
here and put it over here take out a
negative energy electron from from what
has become called the
deri the daxi this incredible collection
of electrons which fill the vacuum
remove
it and you have a
hole you have a missing negative energy
electron but you have an extra let's
let's get rid of this one up here you
have an extra positive energy
electron you've made a hole in a
negative energy C and created an extra
positive what is this thing over here
this thing is something it's a missing
uh if electrons have negative charge and
you plunk one out of the vacuum you'll
be left with a little bit of a hole and
the hole will have positive charge what
about its energy what will be the energy
of this hole
here
H yeah it will be exactly the same as
the electron it won't be
negative removing a negative energ
puts in a positive
energy okay removing a negative energy
increases the energy so by removing a
particle from here you put an extra
particle here but you've also created a
negative energy hole sorry a positive
energy hole in the negative energy C and
that's called a
positron that's called a
positron
uh his ically der did not know at first
that he was talking about a thing which
was a identical to the electron except
for the sign of its charge why does it
have opposite charge well when you fill
because it's a missing negative energy
electron a missing negative energy is
the same as a positive energy so dra
said this uh this solves his problem he
now has a stable vacuum there are no
negative energy particles there are only
positive energy electrons and positive
energy
positrons uh or positive
holes and this then solves the problem
and it does it does solve the problem
yeah theic because this picture suggests
there always be equal numbers of electr
not necessarily you could start with
some excess electrons or you could start
with some holes with no uh with no
electrons not
necessarily um if you interpret it by
saying you started somehow just with a
vacuum yeah then it's kind of true but
there's no reason to start with only the
vacuum you could start with some excess
of one kind or the other but um let's
think about something else for a moment
uh okay so we start with let's start
with a
vacuum we start with the vacuum which
means all the negative energy States
filled
up and then a photon comes along now
think about a photon coming and hitting
an atom it finds an electron and kicks
the electron upstairs right it kicks it
up to uh to higher
energy same thing will happen
here a photon comes
along waxs an
electron there's no electrons up here
but this thing is full of electrons full
of negative energy electrons it hits it
and takes one of the electrons from here
and puts it upstairs increases its
energy it can't decrease its energy cuz
they're all
filled all it can do is put it into the
upstairs here and leave a
hole okay so what's happened what's
happened is a photon has come along
and turned itself into a negative energy
sorry a posit negative charge electron a
positron and an
electron we as a matter of convention we
always draw the electron lines with
arrows in them that point up and
positrons with arrows that point down
that's just a
convention uh but it's kind of a nice
convention
it's a nice convention okay positrons
Point down electrons point up and just
remember that whenever you slice this at
a moment of
time every particle that you slice with
an upgoing arrow is a negative charge
because it's an electron and every
um particle that you cross that has a
down goinging arrow has a uh a positive
charge so
this is
uh the direct theory of electrons let's
talk about the field operators
describing them the field operators are
built exactly the same
way as the Bon field operators
s it's built as an integral over the
momentum
DP creation and Annihilation operators
for particles of given momentum let's
take uh the side the um this one here
that's uh a minus the annihilation
operator for a particle of momentum P
time e to the I guess it's minus I PX if
I'm not
mistaken yeah Annihilation has e to the
minus
ipx or is it e to the plus
ipx doesn't
matter okay that's the way we built
field operators creation operators and
Annihilation operators times um times
this sort of thing here but now these
are firion creation Annihilation
operators they anti-c commute with each
other okay well what what do we
integrate p over we integrate P from
minus infinity to plus infinity but that
means that there are negative energy
particles in here because negative
energy corresponds to minus momentum
negative
momentum right there are negative energy
electrons in this formula here but let's
divide it up into two pieces an integral
from 0 to Infinity
DP Annihilation operator for a positive
momentum or a positive energy electron e
to Theus I
PX and another term from minus infinity
to zero
DP creation operator now for a oh did I
write I meant Annihilation operator my
mistake
Annihilation operator
here same thing as here Annihilation
operator for a negative momentum
particle now D said wait a minute
actually I'm not sure who said it I said
when you're dealing with firmians the
mathematics does not distinguish
creation operators from Annihilation
operators you can in the meth
mathematics say that every Annihilation
operator is a creation operator that's
because they anti- commute mathematics
just doesn't distinguish them so instead
of calling this an Annihilation operator
for a negative energy particle let's
just relabel it and call it a creation
operator for a
positron what does it do remember what
it did it annihilated a negative energy
electron in other words it created a
positron so let's just call this
Annihilation operator of a negative
energy particle let's call it a creation
operator for a
positron and he labeled them B's B's I
don't know why B's but A's and B's
electrons
positrons and I think if you work it out
and do the uh a little bit of juggling
you'll get from zero to Infinity again
but you get e to the I think you get e
to the plus I PX yeah you do I
think so D said you can think of the
field operator as a sum of two terms one
with Annihilation operators for
electrons and the other with creation
operators for
positrons
um I'll give you one example of the kind
of thing this does for you the field
operator has two kinds of things so
let's let's let's take let's take a
process where an electron comes
along emits another electron and a
photon this would be an Annihilation
operator an Annihilation operator for an
electron that's an A minus and a
creation operator for another electron
that's a that's an A+ and a photon
operator let's call a photon operator
a
okay you might suspect that where this
comes from and you'd be right is a term
in the hamiltonian which would be side
Dagger of
x times s of
X time a an Annihilation operator a
creation operator and a photon operator
but now if you put in the fact that the
operator here have two pieces one with
creation operators of one kind of
particle and the other Annihilation and
and the annihilation operators the other
kind of particle what you find out is
that the same operator has contributions
in it which is not an electron being an
electron and becoming a photon but in
fact for example an electron
annihilating a positron electron
positron Photon if you look around for
all the creation ation operators in here
you find that that contains combinations
the same operator the same operator
which took an electron to an electron
and a photon takes an electron and a
positron and makes a photon so one
simple complex of field operators
describes many many processes there's
even another one an electron and a
positron can be created and a photon at
the same time just by using all the
various varieties of creation and
Annihilation operators that would happen
in here this was the start sort of aan
diagrams course it was Fineman who
figured out how to evaluate them and
make real sense out of them but uh durak
had quite a bit of the structure uh
down and that brings us I think to the
end for
tonight so yeah can you say um how do
modern physicists think about this Asos
to to using the direct
C oh no oh very easy they just say
forget the direct C just
replace replace creation operators for
negative energy by Annihilation
operators for positive energy just do
that flip in the uh in the formulas and
when you do that then it becomes
completely symmetric in the electrons
and
positrons you discover right away that
it's a complete symmetry so you could
think of the uh of the vacuum
as being filled with negative energy
positrons and the holes being electrons
right okay one last thing is that uh
this same pattern turns up in solid
state
physics if you have a um a crystal or
anything else for that matter with uh
with lots of electrons in it and you
want to know what the lowest energy
state is you just put all however many
electrons you have you put them into the
lowest available
States right you just uh if the ground
state is not occupied you put an
electron in there they're of course
they're all positive but you keep
putting electrons in until you fill it
up to some level what level however many
electrons you have you fill it up so
then you have a ground state and the
ground state is full of electrons the
net charge of course is zero because
there are protons there also canceling
the charge so you have a C it's called
the firy C what firmy had to do with it
I'm not
sure uh now you can take an electron out
of the sea and kick it upstairs to a
higher energy state that leaves a hole
sure enough it leaves a hole those are
called in solid state physics they're
called holes but they can also be
thought of as posit as positive charged
particles so in solid state part of
physics you have exactly the same thing
you have electrons which have energy up
above the fmy level up above this filled
sea and you also have positive charges
which are really just really this time
just really the missing electrons in the
uh and of course the positrons also or
not the positrons the holes also have
positive energy because they correspond
to a missing energy at a lower energy
level it uh well they they do have um
positive energy so the same pattern is
very well known in solid state physics
but D did this first I always thought
that draak patterned this on what
happens to electrons in a
crystal until I realized that he did
this long before anybody had thought
about electrons and crystals and uh so
yeah I just wondering if the like the
kle Gordon equation for BS does have a
problem with cascading to the no no no
no um no it doesn't we don't have time
to go through it but
uh comes from what's that spin for BOS
the spin one for BOS where do they come
from not from
this not from
this
yeah in the direct equ when they became
Fair what was it that told you fair that
it had to be firion in order to solve
this negative energy
problem if without without uh without
having firion you could just keep
filling up more and more and more uh
negative energy particles and the vacuum
would just be
unstable um you take an
atom the atom can Decay but let's take
the ground state of the atom why can't
the ground state of the atom decay by
producing a photon well because there's
no energy level of the electron below
that it's got to produce a positive
energy Photon because there are only
positive energy
photons so that means an electron in the
lowest
energy it can't Decay any further
because it's down at the bottom but
Suppose there was a whole bunch of
negative energy states of the
electron then no matter how many of them
you filled up you could always add
another one to the negative energy
states and have the atom
Decay by having the electrons sink down
even
lower what prevents that what prevents
that is the electrons are already there
but it can only prevent it if they're
fion it's not a direct equation it's a
Klein Gordon equation which is different
different and does not have the form H
is equal to a linear function of
P it's a more complicated uh
uh right so you can look up now the
Klein Gordon equation for bans we just
don't have time for it now but I think
you're probably in a good position to to
follow it and it's a a very different
structure a very different structure
doesn't have directa matrices doesn't
uhor Elon is to the annihilation
aitron but negative energy positron but
there a difference
and not quite the same there which
applies to me degree of freed another
degree of Freedom which would be
charge yeah yeah well it's not really a
degree of Freedom every electron has a
negative charge every positron has a
positive
charge um but
yeah uh
okay one way of thinking about
it it's sort of semi correct but one way
of thinking about it is these 4x4
matrices there are two binary things
going on one binary thing is a spin and
the other binary thing is whether it's
an electron or a positron now that's not
quite right but it's it's a reasonable
counting of how many different states
you have
right won't the uh infinite caus an
infite cosmological
constant there you
[Laughter]
go
yeah
right and uh
right you can either think of it as the
energy in the direct sea
but you can also just think of it as the
zero point
oscillation of the fields photons you
don't usually think of is filling up um
a dxi but they also contribute vacuum
energy a half har bar Omega for every
uh for
every oscillating mode of the of the
electromagnetic field and that's also
infinite now it is true that for the
photons and for bosons in general a
curious fact is that um for photons the
vacuum energy is
positive for fans it's always negative
so you could imagine cancelling them and
uh but unfortunately the
um they don't really cancel because the
electron has a mass the photon doesn't
have a mass
and right you're always left over with
some huge amount of vacuum energy right
so you're you're
right that's that's right but keep in
mind the only time that the zero point
of energy comes into anything is when
that energy is
gravitating uh for all other purposes
the zero point of energy can just be
subtracted off and neglected because it
doesn't come into any energy differences
it's only when you say wait a minute
energy gravitates that uh that you have
to worry about it
okay yeah one more can you say more
about how Mass relates to and Right
Moving it's just a term in the
hamiltonian which switches from one to
the other that's all I can
say and
uh you can like if you like to try to
picture it you can try to picture it but
uh it's always these pictures are always
defective so I I won't say anymore I if
if I had more to say I would have said
it
okay for more please visit us at
stanford.edu